Last year, SEO fundamentally changed.
Traffic was down across the board.
People were in full-on panic mode. Some
even pivoted to new professions. Sites
that had ranked for years were bleeding
out. But worse than the losses was the
uncertainty. No one knew what was coming
or if SEO even had a future. And the
data's brutal. Our research from April
showed that when an AI overview appears
in search results, the number one
ranking page loses about 35% of its
clicks. And we just reran that study and
it's now a 58% loss. But what's changed
is that we finally have some answers
because last year's turmoil revealed
three key shifts in search behavior that
give us hints into where SEO may be
going. And it all starts by
understanding how discovery works today.
So, I bought these headphones about a
month ago and I started on Google. I
searched for best headphones, clicked on
a few listicles, jotted down some common
models, and I didn't actually read a
thing. But I went to Reddit to see what
people were saying about those models.
Then I hit YouTube to watch dedicated
reviews and comparisons. And when I
finally went to the store to pick one
up, I was reading Amazon reviews on my
phone just to make sure I was making the
right purchase. This buying journey
might sound exhaustive, [music] but it's
not unusual. Information has never been
more accessible and we've been
researching like this for years. And
while this might not seem like it has
anything to do with SEO, it has [music]
everything to do with it because AI
assistants are learning the same way we
do. They're researching YouTube, Reddit,
forums, review sites, and using all of
it to decide who to recommend. In fact,
86% of the top cited sources are unique
to each AI assistant. Google AI
overviews lean heavily on YouTube,
Reddit, and Quora. ChatGPT prefers
publishers and news outlets and
Perplexity tends to cite niche and
regional sites. But that doesn't mean
getting mentioned on these domains will
automatically put you in AI overviews
because every niche and topic is
different. [music] So, to see the
websites being mentioned in your niche,
you need to reverse engineer the
competition. Just go to Ahrefs Brand
Radar with your brand and your
competitors' brand set, then open the
cited domains report. From here, you can
see the exact websites AI assistants are
citing in the queries where you and your
competitors are mentioned. But showing
up on these domains isn't enough. AI
pulls from specific pages and the pages
it chooses to cite is all based on the
second shift. Brand is everything. When
you type something like best smartphone
for photography into an AI assistant, it
doesn't just spit out an answer from
memory. [music] It fans that single
query out into dozens of smaller
subqueries. Things like iPhone 17 Pro
versus Samsung Galaxy S25 Ultra camera,
best phone for low-light photos,
smartphone with best zoom lens in 2026.
Then it pulls information from the pages
that rank for each of these subqueries
and stitches it all together into one
answer. This is called query fanout and
it's how most AI assistants work. So, if
your brand is mentioned across the pages
that rank for those subqueries, you have
a much better chance of being included
in the final response. In fact, our
research shows that branded mentions
have the strongest correlation with
visibility in Google's AI overviews.
More than backlinks, referring domains,
and domain rating. To find the right
pages to get mentioned on, go to Ahrefs
Brand Radar, enter your brand, your
competitors, and your niche, then open
the cited pages report. Add a filter
where the query contains words like
best, top, versus, review, or
alternative. And these are the
predictable fanout queries AI tends to
use. Now you have a list of the exact
pages worth getting mentioned on, which
will mostly be list roundups, comparison
posts, and dedicated reviews. Reach out
to the authors and try to get your
product reviewed there. Send them free
samples or do whatever you need to to
get your mention there. But here's the
thing, even if you get mentioned on AI
overviews and different chatbots,
there's still a massive chunk of search
where traditional SEO still wins. And
that's the third shift. Organic clicks
are flowing to action. Here's the deal.
Google's AI search is still very much in
its formative years.
>> [music]
>> It's great at answering questions,
summarizing large amounts of content,
and providing decent recommendations.
But it can't really do anything
meaningful for you. Not yet at least.
Like when someone searches backlink
checker, snow removal service, or
mortgage calculator, Google or any
chatbot isn't going to satisfy that
query with information alone because
that's not what people want. They're
looking to complete an action. Now,
compare that to informational queries
like what is a mortgage? AI overview.
How to calculate BMI? AI overview. What
is compound interest? AI overview.
That's why AI overviews don't really
exist for these types of action-driven
queries because Google knows the user
needs to click somewhere or decide
something to get what they want. And
that's ultimately the goal of Google,
deliver the best result for any given
query. This is where traditional SEO,
content, links, and technical still work
like a charm. So, if there's one thing
you must do before you target a query,
is answer this question. Can AI fully
satisfy the user for this query? If the
answer is no and the query has value for
your business, you really need to
consider targeting the traditional way.
Now, if you already have a list of
keywords, go through them and ask
yourself that question. But if you want
to find these opportunities in bulk, you
can do that with a neat little trick in
the keyword research tool. Just enter
broad seeds related to your niche, then
head to the matching terms report. Add
an include filter with modifiers like
calculator, checker, generator, and
more. These will all be action-oriented
queries because they're for free tools.
So, the typical content and links game
should still be valid here. Now, if
tools aren't your thing, another quick
way to find queries that will likely get
organic clicks is to filter for
transactional queries. All you have to
do is choose transactional in the
intense filter and you'll have a list of
queries that people search when they
want to transact or do something. SEO
has changed, no doubt. The main thing
being that you need to be discoverable
everywhere. Focus on building a brand
that gets mentioned on important pages
like lists, comparisons, review sites,
and social media all while remembering
that the fundamentals of SEO, yes, the
old version, isn't dead. The game hasn't
ended. You just need to split your
attention into these three buckets and
adapt to search with searchers as their
behavior changes.